<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects on araboud.ca</title><link>https://araboud.ca/projects/</link><description>Recent content in Projects on araboud.ca</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 19:45:00 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://araboud.ca/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Pandion VTOL Drone</title><link>https://araboud.ca/projects/pandion_overview/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 19:45:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://araboud.ca/projects/pandion_overview/</guid><description>A scratch-built R/C VTOL aircraft.
I have started getting into R/C aircraft recently and have been building a small twin rotor VTOL. The eventual plan is for it to be an aerial imaging platform that doesn&amp;rsquo;t need a runway for launch and retrieval. For now, just getting it to hover stably has been quite the challenge.
Configuration Initially I had planned on this being a tri-copter with even distribution and forward sweeping wings on conversion, but this had a lot of un-needed complexity and the cost of the rear engine would be high.</description></item><item><title>Not Another Task Manager (GoNATM)</title><link>https://araboud.ca/projects/gonatm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 19:30:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://araboud.ca/projects/gonatm/</guid><description>ReactJS task managment app with Golang back-end.
I usually use Trello for tracking tasks in home projects, but have been interested in logging time. This was a good excuse to try out a proper React app with Golang back-end. I have found Gin very handy and I think it will be my server of choice for Go moving forward.
Feel free to check out the project on github but be warned that it is very much a work in progress.</description></item><item><title>CBC Pi Radio</title><link>https://araboud.ca/projects/cbcpi/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 19:30:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://araboud.ca/projects/cbcpi/</guid><description>Raspberry Pi internet radio.
This small 3d-printed internet radio was a gift for a CBC fan. It also served to get some more experience in Fusion 360. This project was short and sweet as the scope was concrete from the beginning, and it didn&amp;rsquo;t require a lot of custom work.
The radio is powered a Raspberry Pi Zero, an amplifier bonnet, and 2 small speakers.
I posted the design to thingiverse with detailed instructions.</description></item></channel></rss>