<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Raspberry Pi on araboud.ca</title><link>https://araboud.ca/tags/raspberry-pi/</link><description>Recent content in Raspberry Pi on araboud.ca</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><copyright>Copyright © 2008–2021, Alex Raboud; all rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://araboud.ca/tags/raspberry-pi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>LaseCap Bird Abatement</title><link>https://araboud.ca/projects/lasecap/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://araboud.ca/projects/lasecap/</guid><description>
&lt;p>A friend of mine who owns a berry farm mentioned that a lot of yield is lost to birds accross the whole industry. Farmers will use various devices like nets and propane noise-makers to try and keep them away from the crops. One of the modern devices is a laser that scans the ground to scare-off flocks. These devices are quite large and expensive which lead me to try developing a smaller scale version with better software options.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Earlier designs incorporated a boresight camera to view where the laser was aiming. This was simplified to a &amp;quot;sprinkler&amp;quot; style system that would scan a specified area at interval.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/lasecap/lasecap_frame.png" alt="LaseCap frame with exposed belt drive.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A stepper motor drives the pan rotation via a timing belt. All connections to the top go through a slip ring so the laser can rotate continuously. A hall sensor is used to &amp;quot;zero&amp;quot; the bearing of the laser. The pitch of the laser is controlled by a servo.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/lasecap/lasecap_case_open.png" alt="LaseCap case with top removed">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Everything is encased in sealed plastic container, with a length of clear PVC similar to a lighthouse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/lasecap/lasecap_board.png" alt="LaseCap custom hat PCB">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The device is controlled by a Raspberry Pi 3+ with a custom hat PCB and PWM controller.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/lasecap/lasecap_render.png" alt="LaseCap full render">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CBC Pi Radio</title><link>https://araboud.ca/projects/cbcpi/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://araboud.ca/projects/cbcpi/</guid><description>
&lt;p>This small 3d-printed internet radio was a gift for a CBC fan. It also served to get some more experience in Fusion 360. This project was short and sweet as the scope was concrete from the beginning, and it didn't require a lot of custom work.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/cbcpi/exploded.png" alt="Render of internet radio with separate pieces">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The radio is powered a Raspberry Pi Zero, an amplifier bonnet, and 2 small speakers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/cbcpi/irl_radio.png" alt="Picture of finished internet radio">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I posted the design to &lt;a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:3336206">thingiverse&lt;/a> with detailed instructions.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>