<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>R/C on araboud.ca</title><link>https://araboud.ca/tags/r/c/</link><description>Recent content in R/C on araboud.ca</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><copyright>Copyright © 2008–2021, Alex Raboud; all rights reserved.</copyright><atom:link href="https://araboud.ca/tags/r/c/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Pandion VTOL Drone</title><link>https://araboud.ca/projects/pandion_overview/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://araboud.ca/projects/pandion_overview/</guid><description>
&lt;p>I have started getting into R/C aircraft recently and have been building a small twin rotor VTOL. The eventual plan is for it to be an aerial imaging platform that doesn't need a runway for launch and retrieval. For now, just getting it to hover stably has been quite the challenge.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="configuration">Configuration&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Initially I had planned on this being a tri-copter with even distribution and forward sweeping wings on conversion, but this had a lot of un-needed complexity and the cost of the rear engine would be high.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/pandion/PandionAssemblyRender.png" alt="Latest rendering of Pandion VTOL">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The main concern was to put the C of G in the right positionon during forward flight and being able to balance while hovering. I've been getting more comfortable with Fusion 360 and it is an amazing tool to work with. I took the time to add the approximate weight of materials and the balance and weight was quite close in the finished product.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The latest configuration is pretty close to a V-22 Osprey so the genus Pandion seemed like an appropriate name. The ducted fan in the rear is purely for pitch control so I would consider it a bi-copter.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I've seen other bi-copters that will balance 2 axes, but it has been nice to have one control motion per axis with the ducted fan handling pitch. Initially, I used small geared motors with encoders, but I had difficulty getting them to run consistently.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/pandion/early_rotary_encoder.png" alt="Early wing design using geared motors">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>9g servos in the nacelles provide yaw control when hovering and role control in forward flight.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="materials">Materials&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>You'll notice I originally used a carbon fibre main-spar and the axle for the nacelle. The extruded tube I used originally tended to crack and I had much better results with a proper weaved fibre tube later on. In early versions, I also used aluminum tig wire in combination as stringers in the wing. Later designs used aluminum c-channel for the main spar and a wooden rear spar which provide plenty of support.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/pandion/channel_wing.png" alt="Channel wing construction">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>9g servos controlled the nacelle pitch and fine engine pitch control. While testing, I stripped a few nylon gear servos since the nacelles are quite front heavy. After replacing them with metal-gear servos, there hasn't been any problems. PLA has worked well for the wing ribs and various pieces. At some point, I may try out foam filament.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="electronics">Electronics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I've used an MPU-6050 gyro, a FlySky receiver, 3 small ESCs, 3 buck-converters, and an ESP-32 to control everything. A flight controller would have made things easier, but part of the challenge was writing the software from scratch. Also there is not a lot of control software that will change between configurations at run-time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/pandion/control_board.png" alt="Control Board">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I then mounted the control board to the wing on a pivoting test stand to help develop the control software.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/pandion/test_stand.gif" alt="GIF of wing on test stand">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Foam core with hot glue has been great to use for the wing covering and fuselage. It's easy and quick to work with when prototyping like this.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="software">Software&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="github.com/ataboo/pandion">Pandion VTOL&lt;/a> repo has all the software for the project. Early on, I used some arduino sketches, but I've found ESP-IDF is easier to develop for a project like this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The gyro is read over I&lt;sup>2&lt;/sup>C so this was fairly easy to implement. I ended up polling periodically, but I may look into using interrupts at some point.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I managed to reverse engineer the FlySky receiver with the help of a logic analyzer. Currently I'm providing the battery voltage as a sensor with a simple voltage divider, but the ground-work is there in-case I need more. The channel values are read on another pin digitally.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/pandion/ibus_sensor_still.png" alt="I-Bus sensor output on receiver">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Getting d-shot to work for the ESCs was a little tricky, but the logic analyzer and the output from a flight controller helped me tune the timing. I flashed the rear ESC with BL Heli to make it reversable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I've implemented a PID controller with a positive and neutral stability mode. I then wrote a tcp server so the ESP-32 acts as a WiFi hot-spot, for updating values remotely. I then created a &lt;a href="https://github.com/ataboo/pandion-tcp-client">client in fyne&lt;/a> to send commands and this has made tuning the PID values much easier.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="will-it-fly">Will it Fly?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/pandion/pandion_flight_min.gif" alt="Basement flight test">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The stability needs some work, but the power to weight to weight is plenty.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/pandion/garage_test.png" alt="Garage Test">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I will keep tuning the controls until I feel confident in its ability to hold station. Once that is done, I should be able to tune for forward flight with the safety net of hovering.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>