<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Golang on araboud.ca</title><link>https://araboud.ca/tags/golang/</link><description>Recent content in Golang on araboud.ca</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><copyright>Copyright © 2008–2021, Alex Raboud; all rights reserved.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://araboud.ca/tags/golang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Not Another Task Manager (GoNATM)</title><link>https://araboud.ca/projects/gonatm/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://araboud.ca/projects/gonatm/</guid><description>
&lt;p>I usually use Trello for tracking tasks in home projects, but have been interested in logging time. This was a good excuse to try out a proper React app with Golang back-end. I have found Gin very handy and I think it will be my server of choice for Go moving forward.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Feel free to check out the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ataboo/go-natm.git">project on github&lt;/a> but be warned that it is very much a work in progress.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>LaseCap Bird Abatement</title><link>https://araboud.ca/projects/lasecap/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://araboud.ca/projects/lasecap/</guid><description>
&lt;p>A friend of mine who owns a berry farm mentioned that a lot of yield is lost to birds accross the whole industry. Farmers will use various devices like nets and propane noise-makers to try and keep them away from the crops. One of the modern devices is a laser that scans the ground to scare-off flocks. These devices are quite large and expensive which lead me to try developing a smaller scale version with better software options.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Earlier designs incorporated a boresight camera to view where the laser was aiming. This was simplified to a &amp;quot;sprinkler&amp;quot; style system that would scan a specified area at interval.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/lasecap/lasecap_frame.png" alt="LaseCap frame with exposed belt drive.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A stepper motor drives the pan rotation via a timing belt. All connections to the top go through a slip ring so the laser can rotate continuously. A hall sensor is used to &amp;quot;zero&amp;quot; the bearing of the laser. The pitch of the laser is controlled by a servo.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/lasecap/lasecap_case_open.png" alt="LaseCap case with top removed">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Everything is encased in sealed plastic container, with a length of clear PVC similar to a lighthouse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/lasecap/lasecap_board.png" alt="LaseCap custom hat PCB">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The device is controlled by a Raspberry Pi 3+ with a custom hat PCB and PWM controller.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://araboud.ca/imgs/lasecap/lasecap_render.png" alt="LaseCap full render">&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>